Finding Aid for Donald B. Canham Papers 1968-1988
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Don Canham Papers 1968-1988
Canham, Don.
89172 Aa 2
University of Michigan track coach, 1948-1968 and athletic director, 1968-1988, NCAA high jump champion, 1941. Papers primarily document his tenure as athletic director and activities with National Collegiate Athletic Association, Big Ten Conference and track coaches associations.
5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection (Donor No. 7572 ) was given by Donald B. Canham to the library in 1988. Periodic additions are expected.
The collection is open for research.
Donald B. Canham was track coach, 1948-1968, and Director of Athletics1968-1988, at the University of Michigan. He competed in track for Michigan 1937-1941, winning the NCAA high jump championship in 1941.
On July 1, 1968, Donald B. Canham was appointed to succeed Herbert O. Crisler as the fifth athletic director in University of Michigan history. A native of Oak Park,Illinois, Canham was born on April 27, 1918. He attended the University of Michigan from 1937 until 1941 during which time he won Big Ten and National Collegiate Athletic Association championships in the high jump. He graduated with a bachelor's degree in physical education, history, and science.
Upon discharge from military service in 1946, Canham returned to the University of Michigan as an assistant track and field coach. In 1948 he was promoted to head coach in that sport. During his 19 year tenure leading the track and field team, he won 12 conference championships and compiled a winning record of .800 in all regular season contests.
In 1954, while still coaching, Canham started an independent distributing company marketing instructional films and recreational and athletic equipment. School-Tech, Inc., has since expanded into a multi-million dollar operation. His experience in developing and promoting a line of products in addition to his successful coaching background were factors that contributed to Canham's later successes as athletic director.
From 1968 until his retirement from university service in 1988, Don Canham directed the athletic program at the University of Michigan with one eye on the financial bottom line. He became a leading practitioner and advocate for aggressive marketing of the college athletic experience. In addition, he insisted on programs noted as much for their scandal-free reputations as for their winning records. His coaches won nearly 70 conference championships without a single warning or penalty from the National Collegiate Athletic Association.
During the 1980s, Canham's athletic program regularly ranked among the largest and most self-sufficient in the nation. In the latter ten years of his directorship, Canham established a collegiate record by selling more than 100,000 tickets for every home football game on Michigan's schedule. Augmenting this income with regular football bowl appearances, astute television contracts,and rigorous cost containment measures, his budgets were frequently large enough to support all of his intercollegiate athletic teams and many recreational programs as well.
Canham was very active in the Big Ten conference athletic administration, was a leading member of several national athletic associations, and was a recognized member of the international track and field coaching fraternity.
Shortly after Canham's retirement, the Donald B. Canham Natatorium on the University of Michigan campus was completed and was dedicated in his honor.
The files have been arranged in four series: Personal, Athletic Department, Big Ten Conference, and National Organizations.
The Donald B. Canham papers, 1968-1988, comprise five linear feet of material documenting Canham's tenure as athletic director at the University of Michigan. The papers include extensive departmental correspondence with coaches and administrative staff members, several television contract files, Big Ten Conference administrative minutes, and a variety of materials from several national athletic organizations. Of particular note in the Personal series are several interviews, newspaper feature articles, and speeches that focus upon Canham's philosophy, goals, and accomplishments as an athletic director.
Subject Terms
Athletics--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Canham, Don.; Intercollegiate Conference of Faculty Representatives.; National Collegiate Athletic Association.; University of Michigan--Sports.; University of Michigan. Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics.; University of Michigan. Athletic Dept.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Football.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Canham, Don.
- Personal
  The Personal series includes biographical information, personal correspondence, texts of interviews and speeches and photographs. The photographs file includes formal and informal portraits, a number of group shots and several photos of Canham as University of Michigan track athlete.
  - Biography (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Interviews (Box 1)
  - Speeches (Box 1)
- Athletic Department
  The Athletic Department files contain the bulk of the collection material. Included in this series are documents outlining preparations for nine football bowl appearances, several files relating to recreational and intramural facilities, and extensive documentation of the women's athletic programs and Title IX implementation. The Title IX issue involved development, enhancement, and support of equal athletic opportunities for women. In addition, the "Departmental Correspondence" file contains a wide variety of memos and notes indicative of Canham's day-to-day office operations.
  - Academic Athletic Issues 1985 (Box 1)
  - Academic-Athletic Issues 1985, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Academic Advising and Tutoring 1986 (Box 1)
  - Accounting (merchandising and ticket sales) 1980-1984 (Box 1)
  - Admission of Athletes 1981-1982 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Association 1971-1983 (Box 1)
  - Athletic Trainers 1968-1980 (Box 1)
  - Awards (Varsity "M") 1970-1984 (Box 1)
  - Baseball 1969-1984 (Box 1)
  - Basketball 1975-1985 (Box 1)
  - Basketball Tournaments 1981-1984 (Box 1)
  - Bob Ufer Scholarship Fund 1982-1984 (Box 1)
  - Boosters 1971-1986 (Box 1)
  - Budgets 1973-1988, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Cheerleaders 1971-1986 (Box 1)
  - Cheerleaders Controversy 1987 (Box 1)
  - Coleman Estate Bequest 1987 (Box 1)
  - Concessions 1964-1979 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, City of Ann Arbor 1972-1984 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, Departmental 1971-1988 (Box 1)
  - Crisler Arena (Box 1)
  - Drug Testing Policy 1987 (Box 1)
  - Fencing Club 1972 (Box 1)
  - Field House (new) (Box 1)
  - Football Centennial Committee 1979 (Box 1)
  - Football, Orange Bowl January 1976 (Box 1)
  - Football, Rose Bowl January 1977 (Box 1)
  - Football, Rose Bowl January 1978 (Box 1)
  - Football, Rose Bowl January 1979 (Box 1)
  - Football, Gator Bowl December 1979 (Box 1)
  - Football, Rose Bowl January 1981 (Box 2)
  - Football, Bluebonnet Bowl December 1981 (Box 2)
  - Football, Rose Bowl January 1983 (Box 2)
  - Football, Sugar Bowl January 1984 (Box 2)
  - Football, Holiday Bowl December 1984 (Box 2)
  - Football, Rose Bowl Tour 1987 (Box 2)
  - "Freedom of Information Act" Requests 1976-1981 (Box 2)
  - Golf Course (Box 2)
  - Gymnastics 1973-1980 (Box 2)
  - Hockey report 1982/83 (Box 2)
  - Ice Hockey, Central Collegiate Hockey Association 1978-1986 (Box 2)
  - Ice Hockey, Great Lakes Tournament 1980-1987 (Box 2)
  - Ice Hockey, Hazing Incident 1980 (Box 2)
  - Lacrosse 1971-1973 (Box 2)
  - "M" Club 1945-1987 (Box 2)
  - Marching Band 1969-1986 (Box 2)
  - National Football League Games 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - Physical Education Department 1974-1980 (Box 2)
  - Physical Education Department 1982-1984 (Box 2)
  - Promotional and Premium Materials (Box 2)
  - Recreation-Intramural Facilities (Box 2)
  - Recreation-Intramural Programs 1969-1981 (Box 2)
    (3 folders)
  - Television Broadcast Contracts 1979-1985 (Box 2)
  - Television Broadcasts, Football 1979 (Box 2)
  - Television Broadcasts, Pay T.V. Controversy 1983-1984 (Box 2)
  - Television-Radio Broadcast Policies 1980-1986 (Box 2)
  - Ticket Office 1972-1986 (Box 2)
  - Track and Field 1971-1974 (Box 2)
  - Scholarship Award Funds (Box 2)
  - Soccer, Petition for Varsity Status 1987 (Box 2)
  - Summer Camps Manual 1987 (Box 2)
  - Women's Athletic Program (Box 3)
    - General 1971-1988, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Synchronized Swimming 1981-1982 (Box 3)
    - Title IX 1974-1987, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Track and Field Team Controversy (Box 3)
    - Women's "M" Club 1980-1981 (Box 3)
  - Yost Ice Arena (Box 3)
- Big Ten Conference
  The Big Ten Conference series contains seventeen years of athletic directors' minutes and selected committee correspondence.
  - Correspondence, General 1984-1987 (Box 3)
  - Championships Committee 1969-1971 (Box 3)
  - Image Committee 1971-1972 (Box 3)
  - Indoor Track Championships 1984 (Box 3)
  - Licensing Committee 1970 (Box 3)
  - "Pro Use" Committee 1970-1971 (Box 3)
  - Promotion Committee 1972 (Box 3)
  - Salaries 1972-1982 (Box 3)
  - Swimming Championships 1980 (Box 3)
  - Television Contracts 1979-1986 (Box 3)
  - Transition (Title IX) Committee 1982 (Box 3)
  - Athletic Directors Minutes 1969-1986, 5 folders (Box 4)
- National Organizations
  The National Organizations series contains files on N.C.A.A. committees on which Canham served and several national track and field associations.
  - Division 1-A Directors Association 1987-1988 (Box 5)
  - N.C.A.A. Championship Standards Committee 1982-1983 (Box 5)
  - N.C.A.A. Correspondence, General 1971-1987 (Box 5)
  - N.C.A.A. International Relations Committee 1973-1979 (Box 5)
  - N.C.A.A. Promotions Committee 1975-1978 (Box 5)
  - President's Commission on Olympic Sports 1975-1978 (Box 5)
  - U.S. Track and Field Federation 1975-1978 (Box 5)
  - U.S. Track Coaches Association 1971-1975 (Box 5)
  - World University Games 1975 (Box 5)